Boker Tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, good Moed מועד, Moed, today's daf
דף Daf is gimmel ג. Gimmel. It's the same as the day
of the Omer עומר, Omer, so for the next two weeks if
you get the daf דף Daf you can remember the Omer עומר
Omer and vice-versa.
Okay, so third day of the Omer עומר, Omer, third daf דף,
Daf, Horeious gimmel הוריות ג, Horeious Gimmel, but we pick up we're
a little already a little behind, we pick up in the middle
of Beis Amud Beis ב עמוד ב Beis Amud Beis at
where it says like this, Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel. So line starts with word Amar Shmuel אמר שמואל, Amar
Shmuel, it's almost exactly in the middle of Beis Amud Beis ב
עמוד ב. Beis Amud Beis. I don't know where else to describe
it, but the line starts with word Amar Shmuel אמר שמואל. Amar
Shmuel.
Okay, Zo Divrei Rabbi Yehuda זו דברי רבי יהודה. Zo Divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. This position in the Gemara גמרא Gemara that if an individual
follows beis din בית דין, Beis din, they're exempt and beis din
בית דין Beis din is exempt, which totally makes sense. Beis din
בית דין Beis din doesn't bring their special korban קרבן, Korban, you
don't have the majority of the tzibur ציבור, Tzibur, and the individual's
just listening to beis din בית דין, Beis din, why are they
responsible? So that idea that everybody is exempt, that's the position of
Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Zo Divrei Rabbi Yehuda זו דברי
רבי יהודה. Zo Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Aval Chachamim Omrim אבל חכמים אומרים,
Aval Chachamim Omrim, but the sages say, yachid she'asah al pi beis
din chayav יחיד שעשה על פי בית דין חייב, Yachid she'asah al
pi beis din chayav, that if an individual follows beis din בית
דין Beis din and there's no korban קרבן Korban that beis din
בית דין Beis din brings because it's not the majority of the
of of Israel, then that individual has to bring a korban קרבן.
Korban. And again as I said yesterday, this is a very important
principle because you could say what do you mean that person's totally
blameless? Here somebody is, they're not a scholar, they listen to these
great rabbis, and now you're going to tell them that they're liable
for listening to beis din בית דין? Beis din? Where's their guilt,
where's their fault? And this just demonstrates the idea that korbanot קרבנות
Korbanot are not in the Torah תורה Torah one might say they're
not at all about the idea of personal guilt, but they're certainly
not only about the idea of personal guilt. They're the idea about
that there's some objective sin that was done, like you know you
know you walk into a store you break something you got to
sweep up the glass you got to pay for it, I don't
care if it was your fault or not you're the one who
did it. So there was a sin that was done, it created
this tumah טומאה, Tumah, this impurity in the world, it's got to
be cleaned up by a korban קרבן, Korban, okay, and therefore you're
the one who has to bring it. So if beis din בית
דין Beis din isn't bringing a korban קרבן, Korban, you're bringing a
korban קרבן Korban even though you did nothing wrong by listening to
them. Similar to a discussion in the Gemara גמרא Gemara in Shabbat
שבת Shabbat about a tinok shenishba תינוק שנשבה, Tinok shenishba, about an
infant that was taken captive, doesn't even know that he or she
is Jewish, also brings a certain number of korbanot קרבנות Korbanot for
the sins that they do even though they are blameless. Okay, so
that's what the Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say. Aval Chachamim Omrim yachid she'asah
al pi beis din chayav אבל חכמים אומרים יחיד שעשה על פי
בית דין חייב. Aval Chachamim Omrim yachid she'asah al pi beis din
chayav. Mai Rabbi Yehuda מאי רבי יהודה, Mai Rabbi Yehuda, now where's
this Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, where do we see that
this is a debate between Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the Chachamim חכמים? Chachamim? De-tanya דתניא, De-tanya, nefesh achas techete bishgaga נפש
אחת תחטא בשגגה, Nefesh achas techete bishgaga, if one sin if one
soul sins in error ba'asotah בעשותה Ba'asotah when it does one of
the mitzvot מצוות, Mitzvot, okay and that's the classic parsha פרשה Parsha
where it talks about the idea of an individual bringing a korban
קרבן Korban for a sin. A sin that I should just point
out, types of a chatas חטאת Chatas is fundamentally about a sin
that you would get kareis כרת Kareis for, you'd get divine excision
if you were to do it willfully. Okay, so that verse what
do we learn that those things exclude? Harei eilu gimel mi'utim הרי
אלו ג מיעוטים. Harei eilu gimel mi'utim. Those are three words each
of one is limiting. Nefesh נפש, Nefesh, bishgaga בשגגה, Bishgaga, ba'asotah בעשותה.
Ba'asotah. Ba'asotah בעשותה Ba'asotah also means implies by accident too.
Right, that's true. So ha'oseh mi-pi atzmo chayav העושה מפי עצמו חייב,
Ha'oseh mi-pi atzmo chayav, ha'oseh al pi beis din patur העושה על
פי בית
דין פטור. Ha'oseh al pi beis din patur. So we're not going
to that's only one of the things that it excludes, there are
other things that it excludes as well, but one of the things
that it excludes is basically it's like nefesh נפש, Nefesh, like you're
doing it on your own. If you're just doing it because you're
following beis din בית דין, Beis din, then you would be exempt.
Mai rabanan מאי רבנן, Mai rabanan, so that's Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Now how do we know that's Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is not clear, but anyway let's see who are the
rabanan רבנן. Rabanan. De-tanya דתניא De-tanya we taught in a brayta ברייתא.
Brayta. Adayin ani omer miyut kahal she-chatu chayavin she-ein beis din mevi'in
aleihen par עדיין אני אומר מיעוט קהל שחטאו חייבין שאין בית דין
מביאין עליהן פר. Adayin ani omer miyut kahal she-chatu chayavin she-ein beis
din mevi'in aleihen par. I would say that I understand that when
a minority of the congregation of the community sins, then they have
then they're obligated because beis din בית דין Beis din doesn't bring
a cow par פר Par in that case. Rov hakhal she-chatu hayu
peturin רוב הקהל שחטאו היו פטורין. Rov hakhal she-chatu hayu peturin. I
might think that if the majority of the community sins, maybe the
community should be exempt. Why? She-harei beis din mevi'in aleihen par שהרי
בית דין מביאין עליהן פר, She-harei beis din mevi'in aleihen par, because
beis din בית דין Beis din would bring a cow par פר
Par for that case, their special sacrifice. Talmud lomar תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar me'am ha'aretz מעם הארץ Me'am ha'aretz from the people of the
land, afilu rubah va-afilu kulah אפילו רובה ואפילו כולה, Afilu rubah va-afilu
kulah, even all even the entire community. Now the Gemara's גמרא Gemara
going to say what the heck are we talking about? That says
I understand why a minority brings a korban קרבן, Korban, how do
we know even a majority brings a korban קרבן Korban even if
everybody brings a korban קרבן? Korban? So what does that mean? Everybody
brings a korban קרבן Korban when beis din בית דין Beis din
no, in that case beis din בית דין Beis din brings the
korban קרבן. Korban. So now we're going to have to unpack this
brayta ברייתא. Brayta. Okay, so let's take a look. Bimai במאי, Bimai,
what are we talking about? Ileima bishgagas ma'aseh אילימא בשגגת מעשה, Ileima
bishgagas ma'aseh, so beis din shelo be-hora'ah בית דין שלא בהוראה Beis
din shelo be-hora'ah beis din mai aviditaihu בית דין מאי עבידתייהו? Beis
din mai aviditaihu? So if we're talking about without a you know
with a pure simple shogeg שוגג, Shogeg, without any ruling of beis
din בית דין, Beis din, just when individual sins as individuals. So
then and beis din shelo be-hora'ah בית דין שלא בהוראה Beis din
shelo be-hora'ah and the beis din בית דין Beis din didn't give
any ruling, so beis din mai aviditaihu בית דין מאי עבידתייהו Beis
din mai aviditaihu so then why are we discussing well if the
majority sins... sins, maybe they shouldn't have to bring a קרבן korban
because בית דין Beis Din would bring their קרבן. korban. If we're
just talking about normal sin without a ruling of בית דין, Beis
Din, what do you mean בית דין? Beis Din? You know, of
course if the majority of the community sins all as individuals and
on their own and not based on any ruling they bring a
קרבן korban and why are we comparing it to what בית דין
Beis Din would do? There's no בית דין Beis Din in this
conversation. Okay, so אלא בהוראה, ela behora'ah, so we must be talking
about the case that they received a ruling from בית דין. Beis
Din. והא כתיב מעם הארץ בשגגת מעשה הוא דכתיב. ve-ha ketiv me-am
ha-aretz bishgagat ma'aseh hu de-ketiv. So how do we learn from the
verse by מעם הארץ me-am ha-aretz that even if everybody sins they
still bring a קרבן? korban? Those verses are talking about a case
of a simple שוגג, shogeg, not the context of the ruling of
בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, so you get it? It's a little
confusing here, but anyway it says like this. Okay.
Here's a case of if an individual
sins,
okay, then in that case individual sins, okay,
no קרבן korban for בית דין, Beis Din, so therefore I guess
whatever you know individuals
bring
קרבן. korban. This is what the ברייתא Baraisa says. If the ציבור
tzibur sins
then קרבן korban בית דין Beis Din I guess I'll do
yes קרבן korban
for
בית דין. Beis Din. So therefore I would think okay
that ציבור tzibur
no
קרבן korban
maybe I guess I'll do maybe ציבור tzibur no קרבן korban because
the individual because there is a קרבן korban for בית דין. Beis
Din.
So would the בית דין Beis Din do it if they didn't
make a ruling?
No, that's what the גמרא Gemara is about to say. Okay, so
therefore it says מעם הארץ me-am ha-aretz
okay to tell you
ציבור tzibur brings קרבן. korban. That's the ברייתא. Baraisa. Okay, so now
we're saying what's the case? If the case is that there's no
ruling for בית דין, Beis Din, why are we discussing whether בית
דין Beis Din does or doesn't bring a קרבן? korban? That's irrelevant.
If there's no ruling of בית דין, Beis Din, of course individuals
bring a קרבן korban and the ציבור tzibur bring a קרבן. korban.
Like this whole idea that בית דין Beis Din is bringing a
קרבן korban and that should matter doesn't make sense. If there was
a case of a ruling of בית דין Beis Din and they
followed בית דין, Beis Din, so now I understand. There was a
ruling of בית דין, Beis Din, they followed, I would think since
בית דין Beis Din is bringing the קרבן korban maybe they don't,
מעם הארץ me-am ha-aretz tells you that they do. The problem is
is that מעם הארץ me-am ha-aretz is in a verse that's not
that's not related to בית דין, Beis Din, it's talking just about
a simple sinning of individuals. So how does this tell me that
in a case of a ruling of בית דין Beis Din the
ציבור tzibur is going to bring a קרבן? korban? Okay, so it
doesn't make sense. If there isn't a ruling of בית דין, Beis
Din, I get why they're going to bring a קרבן korban and
why this פסוק pasuk can tell me that, but then why am
I having this discussion over here? And if בית דין Beis Din
did make a ruling, how does this פסוק pasuk teach me anything?
That's not a פסוק pasuk about a case of בית דין Beis
Din making a ruling.
Yeah, it would also lead to the wrong conclusion because we want
the רבנן Rabbanan would say that if the ציבור...
tzibur... Let's not worry about that just now. Right. That's true, but
let's not worry about that just now. Okay, so it says like
this, so it says אלא לאו הכי קאמר ela lav hachi ka'amar
must
be this is how you have to read the ברייתא Baraisa מיעוט
כהאי שחטאו בשוגג בשגגת מעשה חייבין שאין בית דין מביאין עליהם פר
בהוראה mi'ut kehai shechatu beshogeg bishgagat ma'aseh chayavin she'ein Beis Din mevi'in
aleihem par behora'ah הני
חייבין.
hanei chayavin.
Okay. So meaning, if we're talking about there was no ruling of
בית דין, Beis Din, okay? But what we're saying is like this:
if individual sin without any ruling of בית דין, Beis Din, since
in a comparable case where they were following בית דין Beis Din
there wouldn't be a קרבן korban for בית דין Beis Din anyway,
so we get that they bring a קרבן. korban. But if ציבור
tzibur sins, okay,
יכל רוב ציבור שעשו בשגגת מעשה ופטורין שהרי בית דין מביאין עליהם
פר בהוראה yakhol rov tzibur she-asu bishgagat ma'aseh u-pturin she-harei Beis Din
mevi'in aleihem par be-hora'ah תלמוד לומר מעם הארץ אפילו רובו אפילו רובו.
talmud lomar me-am ha-aretz afillu rubo afillu rubo. Okay. So what does
that show you? So the reading is like this: maybe if the
ציבור tzibur sins by themselves, since in a comparable case by בית
דין Beis Din they wouldn't there would be a קרבן korban for
בית דין, Beis Din, so maybe when they sin on themselves they
wouldn't
bring a
קרבן? korban? קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. Anyway but what does
all that tell you? That tells you that
so how does that prove our point?
רבנן Rabbanan? *Rabbanan* have an assumption about the situation of הוראת בית
דין Beis Din *horaat beis din* and the whole ברייתא Braita *braisa*
asks yeah do we imply the same rules when it's שגגת מעשה
shiggas maiseh *shigegas ma'aseh*? Right.
Right. But how does that show you the assumption that the רבנן
rabanan *Rabbanan* hold that in the case of הוראת בית דין Beis
Din *horat beis din* oh the individual is חייב chayav *chayav*? Oh
because what it's saying ah because it's saying yeah exactly because it's
saying like this: in the comparable case no קרבן korban *korban* for
בית דין Beis Din. *beis din* means yes קרבן korban *korban* for
individual. So yes קרבן korban *korban* for the individual. So in this
case I understand when the individual sins by שגגת מעשה shiggas maiseh.
*shigegas ma'aseh* since in the comparable case of ruling of בית דין
Beis Din *beis din* he brings a קרבן korban *korban* he brings
a קרבן korban *korban* here. But in a ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* sins
since in a comparable case no קרבן korban. *korban* for individual for
the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* I should say maybe there'll be no קרבן
korban *korban* for the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* even when there's no ruling
of בית דין Beis Din *beis din* so this tells me there
is a קרבן korban. *korban* when there's no ruling of בית דין
Beis Din, *beis din*. Right. So the fact is we are trying
to make a parallel between שגגת מעשה shiggas maiseh *shigegas ma'aseh* okay
here's the parallel this is a case of שגגת מעשה shiggas maiseh
*shigegas ma'aseh* it was just an accidental act not based on a
ruling and this is a case of הוראת בית דין Beis Din
*horaat beis din*. So we're saying when an individual sins without any
ruling since in a comparable case of following בית דין Beis Din.
*beis din* they would there would be no קרבן korban. *korban* for
בית דין Beis Din. *beis din* meaning and they would bring a
קרבן korban, *korban* so of course individuals are going to bring a
קרבן korban *korban* when they sin. But in a case of a
ציבור tzibbur. *tzibbur* sins since in a comparable case there would be
a קרבן korban. *korban* for בית דין Beis Din, *beis din* and
no קרבן korban *korban* for the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* maybe when they
sin all by themselves they shouldn't bring a קרבן korban. *korban* this
tells me they do bring a קרבן korban *korban*. Right. So that
shows you that an individual following בית דין Beis Din *beis din*
does bring a קרבן korban *korban*. So that's our proof that there's
a position that argues on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
where are we?
ממה
*mima*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
okay where am I? אמר רב Rav's פפה ממה *Amar Rav Pappa
mima*? Who says that's the right reading of the ברייתא Braita *braisa*?
דילמא לא הן ולא בית דין Beis Din *Dilma lo hein velo
beis din*. So maybe you know when maybe the רבנן *Rabbanan* here
really hold here just like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda* that
when an individual sins nobody brings a קרבן korban *korban*. אי הכי
מאי Mai? אריא דקמהדר ארובא לחיובא *Ee hachi mai arya dekammahader aruba
lachiyuva*? לאו מכלל דמיעוטא בהוראה קאימלה דמיחייבו בהוראה *Lav miklal demi'uta behora'ah
kaimleh demichayeivu behora'ah*? So no if that's true that in this case
individuals wouldn't bring a קרבן korban *korban* why do they more trying
to argue
that this why are they more trying to say oh we don't
know if in this case they're going to bring a קרבן korban
*korban*? Right the only reason to assume that there's more of a
קרבן korban. *korban* in a case of individuals is because in the
comparable case of a בית דין Beis Din *beis din* there's a
קרבן korban, *korban*. If in both of these cases of הוראה hora'ah
*hora'ah* there was no קרבן korban. *korban* there's no reason to assume
that there's more of an it's more obvious that there's a קרבן
korban *korban* by the individual than by the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur*. לאו
מכלל דמיעוטא בהוראה קאימלה דמיחייבו בהוראה *Lav miklal demi'uta behora'ah kaimleh demichayeivu
behora'ah*? ונהדר ברישא אמיעוטא דמיחייבי בשגגת מעשה ובסוף נהדר ארובא לחיובא בשגגת
מעשה *venahadar bereisha ami'uta demichayeivei bishgegas ma'aseh uvesof nahadar aruba lachiyuva bishgegas
ma'aseh*? So why does it not just say one minute אי הכי
מאי Mai? אריא דקמהדר ארובא לחיובא לאו מכלל דמיעוטא בהוראה קאימלה *Ee
hachi mai arya dekammahader aruba lachiyuva lav miklal demi'uta behora'ah kaimleh*? Isn't
it clear that when a מיעוט miyut *mi'ut* does הוראה hora'ah *hora'ah*
it's clear דמיחייבו בהוראה *demichayeivu behora'ah*? They're חייב chayav *chayav*. ונהדר ברישא
אמיעוטא דמיחייבי בשגגת מעשה ובסוף נהדר ארובא לחיובא בשגגת מעשה *venahadar bereisha
ami'uta demichayeivei bishgegas ma'aseh uvesof nahadar aruba lachiyuva bishgegas ma'aseh*? Right the
fact that first we said well we know that the individual brings
a קרבן korban *korban* because they bring a קרבן korban, *korban* even
with a ruling of בית דין Beis Din *beis din*. But now
we want to know does a ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* bring a קרבן
korban *korban* because in a case of בית דין Beis Din, *beis
din* they don't? Okay that makes sense. But if in the case
of בית דין Beis Din *beis din* no they would never bring
a קרבן korban *korban* it doesn't make sense to be why the
ברייתא Braita *braisa* is taking this for granted and then going to
the ציבור tzibbur. *tzibbur* case. אלא לאו ela lav, דלא מהדר אמיעוטא
דמיחייבי בשגגת מעשה ובסוף מהדר ארובא לחיובא בשגגת מעשה *Ella lav delo
mahader ami'uta demichayeivei bishgegas ma'aseh uvesof mahader aruba lachiyuva bishgegas ma'aseh*? From
the fact that it is not first try to sort of try
to
prove why didn't it first try to prove the case of the
individual? Why did it take the individual for granted? From the fact
that it did not first try to prove the case of the
individual and then go to prove the case of the ציבור tzibur
*tzibbur* okay שמע מינה Shema mina, מיעוטא בהוראה חייבין הן כשבה ושעירה
ושלא בהוראה בשגגת מעשה חייבין veshelo bahora'ah bishiggas maiseh chayavin *shema mina
mi'uta behora'ah chayavin hein kisba us'ira uveshlo hora'ah bishgegas ma'aseh chayavin* so
you can see from this that when it's a minority who done
it that's when they bring a קרבן korban. *korban* ושלא בהוראה בשגגת
מעשה חייבין *v'shelo b'hora b'shgegas ma'aseh chayavin* okay and therefore it's take
we take for granted that when it's just שגגת מעשה shiggas maiseh
*shigegas ma'aseh* they're also חייב chayav? *chayav*. So that was very wordy
but the basic point was why did the ברייתא Braita *braisa* not
say if this case is that in both of these cases the
individual does not bring a קרבן korban. *korban* then logically you would
have to say is people with me if both in the case
of the individual sinning there's no קרבן korban, *korban* and in the
case of the ציבור tzibur *tzibbur* sinning the individual individuals don't bring
a קרבן, korban. then the ברייתא Braita should have said how do
you know if an individual sins by himself he brings a קרבן
korban since there's no קרבן korban, by בית דין Beis Din and
would have had to prove that and then would say how do
you know a ציבור tzibur has to bring a קרבן Korban. since
there's no קרבן Korban by בית דין Beis Din and would have
had to prove that? But note, that's not the way the ברייתא
Braita operates. The ברייתא Braita doesn't have to prove the case of
the individual because it takes for granted that the individual still brings
a קרבן Korban. with בית דין. Beis Din? So that doesn't have
to be proved, that an individual's שגגת מעשה brings a קרבן. Korban,
The only thing that has to be proven is ציבור tzibur because
ציבור tzibur doesn't bring a קרבן Korban by שגגת מעשה. Okay, so
that was just a very wordy way of saying that the only
structure of the ברייתא Braita that makes sense is if you assume
that in the case of the ruling of בית דין Beis Din
the individual, you know, does bring a קרבן. Korban Otherwise
there would be no explanation why this ברייתא Braita, takes for granted
that by שגגת מעשה the individual brings a קרבן. Korban, All right,
so let's just read that last line. Okay, two lines before the
line gets wide, just שם... shem... אלא לאו מדי דלא מהדר אל
מיעוטא לחיובה בשגגת מעשה Ella lav mide de-lo mahader al miyutai l'chiyuveh
bishiggas maiseh since he did not feel a need to first prove
that in a case of שגגת מעשה the individual brings a קרבן,
Korban, ובסוף מהדר לחיובה בשגגת מעשה u'vesof mahader l'chiyuveh bishiggas maiseh and
then a need to prove the majority. So it didn't need to
prove the case of the individual, it took the individual for granted.
The only logic that it takes individuals for granted is שמע מינה
מיעוט בתראי חייבין הן כשבה ושעירה shma mina miut barei chayavin hein
kisba vesira that when the minority does it with the ruling of
בית דין Beis Din they are still obligated and therefore took it
for granted that שגגת מעשה was obligated, ושלא בהוראה בשגגת מעשה חייבין
and therefore the only thing the ברייתא Braita, had to prove was
the case of the ציבור. tzibbur All right, it's basically just repeating
what we said, that the only way to read the ברייתא braisa
that it makes sense is if it assumes that a majority is
exempt when they follow בית דין, Beis Din but the minority is
obligated. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מכדי תרוייהו סתמי תנן.
michti travaihu stami tenan. Both of these ברייתות Braitas are סתם. stam.
One says that the individual is פטור patur when he follows בית
דין Beis Din, and the other, the way we've unpacked it, assumes
the individual is חייב chayav. when he follows בית דין. Beis Din
ממאי דקמייתא רבי יהודה ובתרייתא רבנן? mimmai de-kamaisa Rabbi Yehuda ve-asra Rabbanan?
How do you know one is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. and one
is the רבנן? אימא איפכא Eima ipcha maybe it's reverse, or maybe
none of them is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda No, מאן תנא סבירא
ליה דדריש מיעוטי כי האי גוונא? man tamseli de-daresh miyutai ki hai
gavna? No, because we know who דרשנים darshens these מיעוטים miyutim like
this: מעם הארץ בעשותה, me'am ha'aretz be'asotah, you know, בשגגה bishgagah
that looks like multiple מיעוטים miyutim in a פסוק. pasuk. So רבי
יהודה היא. Rabbi Yehuda hi. It's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda דתניא, de-tanya, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר: omer:
זאת תורת העולה. zos toras ha-olah. דף ג עמוד א. daf gimmel
amud aleph. הרי אלו שלש מיעוטים. harei elu shalosh miyutim.
This is the תורה Torah of the עולה. olah. Okay, and part
of the problem here as רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos both say
is normally if you have three מיעוט miyut you would say אין
מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות ain miyut achar miyut ella lerabbos that
the second מיעוט miyut is coming to expand. And the fact that
we interpret each מיעוט miyut as excluding something distinct is not to
be taken for granted and that's a particular רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda,
position. Okay, we won't say what he does in that פסוק pasuk
of תורת העולה, Torah ha-olah, that's getting a little off track. Anyway,
that's how we know that there's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. out
there. So our משנה Mishnah that says the individual is פטור patur
is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. but the חכמים, Chachamim, based on what
we've uncovered about this whole comparison, this parallel, presumes that the individual
is חייב chayav. in a קרבן korban? when they're following בית דין.
Beis Din Okay, now the majority,
what, that's in the majority we're talking about, when the majority...
No, רבי... rebbe, what, what, the חכמים Chachamim. assume that when the
individuals follow בית דין, Beis Din they're obligated in a קרבן. korban.
But does it matter whether it was the minority or the majority?
Yes, once it's the majority then once בית דין Beis Din, brings
a קרבן korban. they're exempt. Okay, right, that's exactly it, only as
a minority they're obligated. As a majority, so the somebody, the basic
point is somebody's got to bring a קרבן. korban. That's the way
to think about the חכמים. Chachamim So I accept the fact that
you're a poor individual, you're not to blame, as long as בית
דין Beis Din isn't bringing it, you're bringing it. Once it's the
majority and בית דין Beis Din is bringing it then you're not
going to bring it. ואיבעית אימא עדיין אני אומר לא מצית מוקמת
לה כרבי יהודה. Ve'ibayis eima adayen ani omer lo matzis mokmas lah
ke-Rabbi Yehuda. One minute, I'll still say that you can't say that
there's another reason that this can't be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Why?
דקתני רוב הקהל שחטאו בית דין מביאים על ידיהם פר de-katani rov
hakahal shechatu Beis Din mevi'im al yadeihem par
because this ברייתא Baraisa that presumes that the individual brings a קרבן
korban. says when the majority of the ציבור tzibbur, sins, בית דין
Beis Din brings a פר. par. That's what this ברייתא, Baraisa. right,
this complicated ברייתא, Baraisa what that assumes. ואי רבי יהודה, ve'i Rabbi
Yehuda, and that can't be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda How do you
know? הא אמר ציבור הוא דמייתו בית דין לא. Ha omer tzibbur
hu demayisi Beis Din lav. We know that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda.
says that when actually a majority sins, it is not the קרבן
korban of בית דין, Beis Din. it's a קרבן korban. that the
ציבור tzibbur, brings not as individuals, they're not bringing a million קרבנות,
korbanos, they're bringing one קרבן korban qua the ציבור tzibbur as one
entity of the ציבור. tzibbur Okay, as a collective entity. Correct, but
it's not the בית דין Beis Din who brings it. Okay, we're
going to get to this later. דתנן: de-tan: רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
אומר omer שבעה שבטים שחטאו מביאים שבעה פרים. shiv'ah shevatim shechatu mevi'im
shiv'ah parim. If it was the seven tribes, each tribe is a
separate entity, they bring seven
cows. Basically there's two reasons we know that this, that this ברייתא
braisa is the חכמים Chachamim. and the other is רבי יהודה. Rebbe
Yehuda Number one, the other uses the three מיעוטים, miutim, which is
a רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda approach, and therefore he says when an
individual follows בית דין Beis Din he's exempt, and this one therefore
we'll just assign to the חכמים. Chachamim And the other way you
know that this is not רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and this is
the חכמים Chachamim, is because this one assumes that בית דין Beis
Din, brings the קרבן korban? and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda assumes that
the ציבור tzibbur, as a unit brings the קרבן. korban Okay, so
that's one version, that it's רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda. who's the author.
What?
רב כהנא שכתוב בית דין מביא עליהם פר? Rav Kahana she-katuv Beis
Din mevi aleihem par? Where's that?
It's a משנה Mishna coming up. Oh, okay, we haven't seen it
yet.
Okay, so why should the people bring it if it was the
court's responsibility? They made the error.
Well, we're once back to the idea that it's not so much
a question about guilt, right? So if it's a question about a
sin was done and it has to be fixed, think about it
this way. Now you can still say, okay, you don't need guilt,
but if there is blame and there is guilt, let the court
be the one to do it. Right. That's a good question. At
the end of that day though, they're still the ones that did
it. Nobody was holding a gun to their head. Nobody said you
have to eat חלב. chelev. They said you're allowed to eat it,
right? And the question is like, they still were the ones who
did that act, you know? It's sort of like, I don't know
why this idea comes into my head, but you know I just
heard a story. Like some people bought this property from some guy
and after they bought it they realized that there was like hazardous
material on their property, you know? And so basically the state required
them to do this whole biohazard cleanup cost million dollars, right? They
were completely blameless, the guy who sold it to them knew about
this, but the state wasn't going to run after that guy, they
were running after the people whose property it was on, right? So
why is that? It's that guy's fault. Your property, you got to
clean it up.
What if the guy they bought it from was the court?
Would he be liable? Okay, so they might be able to sue
the guy who brought it to court, but the state's, but the
primary responsibility
is on the person whose property it was on. It's a different
way of thinking about it. It fundamentally doesn't start with an issue
of fault. It starts with an issue that you did it, okay?
And therefore you clean it up.
How about question of נזיקין nezikin with the בית דין?
Beis Din That's a whole other story. Exactly. Exactly. Maybe they can
sue the בית דין Beis Din to pay them back for the
cow. But conceptually if they did the act they have to clean
up the mess. It's a very different way of thinking about it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay. רב נחמן
אמר שמואל, Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, זו דברי רבי מאיר, zu divrei
Rebbe Meir, אבל חכמים אומרים, aval Chachamim omrim, יחיד שעשה על פי
הוראת בית דין חייב. yachid she-asah al pi horat Beis Din chayav.
Now so now we're going to do the same point except rather
than say it's רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, versus the חכמים, Chachamim. we're
going to say it's רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir versus the חכמים. Chachamim
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir is the one that says that if you're
listening to בית דין Beis Din you're exempt, but the חכמים Chachamim
say no, even as long as בית דין Beis Din isn't bringing
the קרבן, korban you are bringing a קרבן.
korban Talking about the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin?
Yes, central בית דין, Beis Din סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Okay, so the same
idea, except now it's רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir versus חכמים Chachamim rather
than רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda,
מאי רבי מאיר מאי רבנן? mai Rebbe Meir mai rabanan? Where do
you see this as a רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir רבנן debate?
דתניא, detanya, תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: הורו ועשו, horu v'asu, רבי מאיר
פוטר וחכמים מחייבין. Rebbe Meir poter v'Chachamim mechayvin.
So who's doing it and who's exempt and who's חייב? chayav. Okay,
so מאן עשו? man asu? Who acted? אילימא בית דין, elima Beis
Din, so בית דין Beis Din. gave a פסק psak and then
בית דין Beis Din themselves followed their own פסק psak and they
acted on it. מאי טעמא דרבנן דמחייבי? mai ta'ama d'rabanan d'mechayvi? So
why are the rabbis saying that בית דין Beis Din is bringing,
you know, a קרבן korban presumably meaning the קרבן korban of בית
דין, Beis Din, not as individuals. והתניא, ve-ha tanya, יכול הורו בית
דין ועשו בית דין יכול יהיו חייבין? yachol horu Beis Din v'asu
Beis Din yachol yehu chayavin? If בית דין Beis Din. gave a
פסק psak and בית דין Beis Din, acted on their own פסק,
psak, maybe that would suffice for בית דין Beis Din to bring
their special קרבן, korban again, not קרבן korban. as individuals who sinned.
תלמוד לומר הקהל ועשו, talmud lomar hakahal v'asu, when the community does,
this is the verse by the special קרבן korban of בית דין.
Beis Din מעשה תלוי בקהל, ma'aseh taluy bakahal, the question of was
it acted upon is a question of did the ציבור tzibur follow.
If the ציבור tzibur. followed, the majority of the community, then that
says
בית דין Beis Din brings their special קרבן. korban והוראה תלויה בבית
דין, ve-hora'ah tluyah b'Beis Din, the פסק psak is בית דין's Beis
Din role, the act is the people's role. Those are the criteria
for bringing this special קרבן. Korban. So when it says if they,
the בית דין, Beis Din? acted, they would bring a קרבן, Korban.
that can't mean the special, if they acted it can't mean בית
דין Beis Din acted and בית דין Beis Din, brings their special
קרבן. Korban? בית דין Beis Din only brings their special קרבן Korban
if the ציבור Tzibur acts, not if they act.
אלא לאו, ela lav, fine, הורו בית דין, horu Beis Din, it
wasn't בית דין Beis Din, who acted. The ציבור Tzibur. acted. הורו
בית דין ועשו רוב הקהל, horu Beis Din v'asu rov hakahal, and
the majority of the community followed them. Okay, so the חכמים Chachamim
say that's your classic case of a קרבן, Korban you're חייב. chayav
So מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר דפוטר? mai ta'ama d'Rebbe Meir d'poter? So
why is רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir saying you're exempt? אלא לאו, fine,
the only way to explain that there's a debate going on here
that makes sense is הורו בית דין ועשו מיעוט הקהל. horu Beis
Din v'asu miut hakahal. It must be בית דין Beis Din, gave
the ruling and individuals followed, a minority of the congregation. ובהא קא
מיפלגי, U'be'ha ka'mifligi, and this is the debate: מר סבר יחיד שעשה
בהוראת בית דין פטור, Mar savar yachid she'asah be'horat Beis Din pattur,
Rabbi Yehuda said, okay, the individual is exempt, he followed בית דין.
Beis Din, ומר סבר יחיד שעשה בהוראת בית דין חייב, U'mar savar
yachid she'asah be'horat Beis Din chayav, and the other says you're חייב.
chayav, So we have a little bit of a vague debate of
an ambiguous, you know, of an unclear debate, what exactly they're debating
about. And we're going to assume and the best read is that
what they're debating about is that Rabbi Meir says when an individual
follows בית דין Beis Din he's פטור pattur and the חכמים Chachamim
say when an individual follows בית דין Beis Din, he's חייב. chayav
So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so Rav Papa who was
the one giving them a hard time previously in the previous עמוד
Amud too, okay, דכולי עלמא de'chulei alma I can tell you everybody
יודה, yodeh, יחיד שעשה בהוראת בית דין פטור, yachid she'asah be'horat Beis
Din pattur, that an individual is exempt like our משנה. Mishnah. אלא
בבית דין משלימו לרוב ציבור קא מיפלגי. Ela be'Beis Din mashlimu le'rov
tzibbur ka'mifligi. Since this ברייתא is so vague as to what they're
debating, I can read a lot of possibilities into it. And now
we're going to have a little fun and an opportunity to like
explore some scenarios that are going to come up in our מסכת.
Masechet. One example would be, okay, let's say you had exactly,
you know, three
million people who followed
בית דין, Beis Din, and you had three million and seventy people
who didn't follow בית דין. Beis Din, And now the בית דין,
Beis Din, all seventy-one of them, followed their own ruling. So do
they get to go, and you count their actions on the side
of the ציבור tzibur, that sinned, and now you have a majority
who sinned? It's like and the hanging chads and all other questions.
Okay, so anyways, says like this: You got it? So whether the
ציבור, tzibur אלא בית דין משלימו לרוב ציבור קא מיפלגי. ela Beis
Din mashlimu le'rov tzibbur ka'mifligi. Do you take their actions and add
it into the tally of did the majority sin or not? Or
are they always seen as a separate entity, even when they go
home and have dinner, you don't count their sins as the sins
of the ציבור, tzibur they're always separate. Okay, מר סבר בית דין
משלימו לרוב ציבור, Mar savar Beis Din mashlimu le'rov tzibbur, so the
חכמים Chachamim who say חייב chayav. would be if you take the
actions of בית דין Beis Din and you add it to the
actions of the ציבור and that's a special קרבן. Korban. ומר סבר
אין בית דין משלימו לרוב ציבור, U'mar savar ein Beis Din mashlimu
le'rov tzibbur, and Rabbi Meir would say no, you don't tally their
sins and there's no special קרבן Korban. in this case, it's only
the minority. Right. Basically. Okay, ואיבעית אימא Ve'iba'is eima if you want
I can tell you, הורו בית דין ועשו רוב של קהל, horu
Beis Din ve'asu rov shel kahal, that the case is like we
thought before, a classic case: בית דין Beit Din gave a ruling
and the majority followed. So then what's the debate? ומאן חכמים רבי
שמעון היא, U'man Chachamim Rabbi Shimon hi, and the when the חכמים
Chachamim say that you are חייב, chayav. that's Rabbi Shimon, דאמר de'amar
I'm sorry, oh, so what do you? דאמר ציבור מייתי, de'amar tzibbur
maysei, because חייב chayav here doesn't mean the בית דין Beit Din.
is חייב. chayav It means is the ציבור חייב. chayav So that's
a hard read, because in that case everybody agrees there's a special
קרבן. korban, The question is who brings it: בית דין Beit Din
or the community? That's your classic case. So we're going to say
that that debate, are you חייב chayav, or פטור, pattur, means is
the community חייב chayav or פטור? pattur? But it's a funny read
of the debate, because really everybody agrees that there's a קרבן, korban,
the just question is is it the community, is it בית דין?
Beit Din That's read number two. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is eima, let's
do the following one. I like read number one better. שבט שעשה
בהוראת בית דינו, Shevet she'asah be'horat Beis dino, that the question is
you don't have the entire כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, you have one
tribe, the שבט Shevet of Dan. Okay, and their בית דין Beit
Din gave a ruling and the majority of the שבט Shevet of
Dan followed it. Is that a case in the תורה Torah of
the special power of the special קרבן korban, of בית דין, Beit
Din. or is the קרבן korban of בית דין Beit Din only
recognized the central court? It's like interesting, right? It's like the state
and the federal court. Right? If you think about it that way,
right? So when we talk about...
but the tribes were in
the time of the Second Temple... it doesn't matter, we're talking about
theoretical, we're going back to biblical times. Okay, so how much do
you view, obviously we're talking about that there's a ציבור, there's a
corporate entity and a central בית דין, Beit Din but the גמרא
Gemara is actually... but your question is appropriate, we tend to stop
thinking in this tribal way, but obviously that's the way it used
to be, so like states and a federal government, and maybe that
would also be a case of one שבט Shevet following. So that's
the scenario. And Rabbi Meir says, no, no special קרבן, korban, we're
only dealing with כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael as a whole. And the
חכמים chachamim say, yes, special קרבן, korban? even individual tribes. Okay, ומאן
חכמים רבי יהודה היא, U'man Chachamim Rabbi Yehuda hi, which is nice,
because then it argues with Rabbi Meir. דתניא, De'tanya, שבט שעשה בהוראת
בית דינו, shevet she'asah be'horat Beis dino, if you have a tribe
following its own בית דין, Beit Din אותו שבט חייב, oso shevet
chayav, that Rabbi Yehuda says that tribe brings. That's read number three
of the ברייתא. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is eima, a lot of good reads
of this ברייתא that don't force us to say that this issue,
that you know, our original reading. Here's read number four: כגון שחטאו
ששה והן רובו של קהל או שבעה אף על פי שאינן רובו
של קהל. kegon she'chatu shisha ve'hein rubo shel kahal o shiva af
al pi she'einan rubo shel kahal. This is great! This is exactly
like the question about majority vote versus the Electoral College. Okay, one
scenario is you got the majority vote but you did not win
the Electoral College. You got six tribes sinned, but it was the...
so it was not the... גם שחטאו ששה והן רובא דקהל Gam
shechat'u shisha ve-hein ruba d'kahal או שבעה אף על פי שאינן רובא
דקהל. O shiva af al pi she-einan ruba d'kahal. This is great.
This is exactly like the question about majority vote versus the electoral
college. Okay, one scenario is, you got the majority vote but you
did not win the electoral college. You got six tribes sinned, but
it was not a majority of tribes, okay, but it was the
majority of the population. Or a flipped situation, okay, which is, you
got seven tribes, you won the electoral college, but it was a
minority of the population. Okay, so is that enough of a רוב
rov to bring to say that the entire community sinned, and you
bring the special קרבן? korban Or do you need both majority of
tribes and majority of population? Okay,
ומתניתין מני u-masnisin mani so the so the one that would say
the חכמים chachamim that would say in that case you're חייב chayiv
even even one of those definitions of majority's enough for חייב, Chayav
is רבי שמעון בן אלעזר? Rebbi Shimon Ben Elazar? He דתניא di-tanya
רבי שמעון אלעזר אומר משמו Rebbi Shimon Elazar omer mishmo in the
name of I forgot who the שמו shmo was of רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir. Oh, yes, I'm sorry. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir I'm
sorry. No, the חטאו ששה והן רובא של קהל או שבעה אף
על פי שאינם רובא של קהל חייבין. chatu shisha ve-hein ruba shel
kahal o shiva af al pi she-einam ruba shel kahal chayavin. Either
definition of majority's enough. So actually it's רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir versus
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, רבי שמעון'ס Rebbi Shimon's version of רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir. So two versions of רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. But anyway,
so the other way of explaining the debate is again not whether
the individual is חייב Chayav? or פטור, patur, but whether a majority
through one measure but not a majority through the other measure is
enough to bring a קרבן. korban, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says no
and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon in the name of רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer says yes. Okay, so now we're done. That was a very
nice little overview of some interesting scenarios and debates around when you
bring a קרבן. korban. But one way or another, we've made the
statement that our משנה mishna says the individual is exempt, but there's
a position out there, says the גמרא, Gemara which has not been
explicit in none of these sources was this opposing position explicit, but
the גמרא Gemara. says there's a position out there call it רבי
rebbe יהודה, call it רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, that said, excuse me,
our משנה mishna is either רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir or רבי rebbe
יהודה, but there's another position out there that the גמרא Gemara is
asserting is the majority position, is the חכמים chachamim position, which would
actually say that when you that that the individual has to bring
a קרבן. korban There can't be a case that there's a sin
and an error, a שוגג shogeg sin, that nobody brings a קרבן.
korban, A sin was done, a קרבן korban has to be brought.
Okay, and that we're saying is the position of the חכמים Chachamim
that even if you as an innocent
trusting individual followed בית דין, Beit Din you're still going to have
to bring a קרבן. korban Okay, but that's not the position of
our משנה. mishna. Now we move on to other topics or related
topics. Since we have been discussing here tribes and majority of ישראל
Yisrael and so on and how do you define a majority of
ישראל, Yisrael, we're going to have a very interesting point right here
that the you know, the religious Zionists sort of love this next
גמרא. Gemara Okay, so let's take a look.
אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, last of the narrow lines. ובהוראה,
U-be-hora'ah, when you come to this issue of a ruling of בית
דין Beit Din and to determine do you have the majority of
the ציבור or not, הלך אחר רוב יושבי ארץ ישראל. Holech achar
rov yoshvei Eretz Yisrael. You do not look at all of כל
ישראל, Klal Yisrael, you only look at those who are living in
ישראל, Israel, in the State of ישראל, Israel, well the country of
ישראל, Israel, okay, which obviously makes sense in the sense that once
we're already talking about tribes and we talk about a central בית
דין, Beit Din the whole concept of a central בית דין, Beit
Din right, puts us back in the תורה'ס Torah's mindset, which is
not Judaism as this ism as this religion which is not linked
to a land, right? The whole idea of a court system and
a בית דין, Beit Din you know, is very much about defining
the law of the land, of the state of, you know, of
the country of ישראל Israel and the people who live in ישראל
Israel and so on. The fact that there might be some people
who live out, that's like a secondary, you know, that's seen as
like, you know, not their prime, you know, whatever, we lose sight
of the fact that we're not just a religion, right? We're a
national identity.
So since the second temple, most Jews lived outside.
Exactly, but now
but what this is doing is it's hearkening back to the verses
and this whole idea of a central בית דין, Beit Din right?
Now people might think oh, if we only had a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
you know, and they think we could maybe, you know, some הלכות
halachos could be different or we would do this or we would
do that, but they're not thinking about the fact that you know,
sometimes people still put that just in the in the fact of
like, you know, if we had a הלכתית halachically there was a
central authority, but losing sight of the idea that a central בית
דין Beit Din means really a central court for the country of
ישראל. Israel. Okay, of the and
so therefore and once that's true, that is defined as the primary
ציבור. You go by רוב יושבי ארץ ישראל. rov yoshvei Eretz Yisrael.
Now the question would be, would he even say this in a
scenario when you know there's like the majority live outside of the
land of ישראל? Israel? Or was he just imagining in a scenario
where you have a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, right, you obviously are going to
have the primary people you know majority of of the people living
in the land itself? All right, but anyway, but assuming that case,
he says you would not take into חשבון cheshbon the, you know,
the what do you call it the what are those called not
expats I guess, right? People who right? People who are living out
yeah. So we would view all Jews outside of ישראל Israel fundamentally
as expats.
Okay, as as Rav Assi. What? You can't vote from abroad.
Right, but that's Israelis living outside of Israel. I'm saying we would
view all Jews living outside of Israel, we wouldn't say you're
Jew... I understand but conceptually that's what it sort of
says you know okay אבל בש- aval besh- okay so it says
ובהוראה הלך אחר רוב יושבי ארץ ישראל uvehora'ah halech achar rov yoshvei
Eretz Yisrael
you go by the majority of those living in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael שנאמר ויעש שלמה בעת ההיא את החג shene'emar vaya'as Shlomo ba'et
hahi et hachag שלמה Shlomo made at that time the חג chag
which is סוכות Sukkot so okay we're a little off in terms
of the רגלים regalim וכל ישראל עמו קהל גדול מלבוא חמת vechol
Yisrael imo kahal gadol milavo Chamat all of Israel was with him
a huge congregation from the ascent of חמת Chamat עד נחל מצרים
ad Nachal Mitzrayim to the wadi of Egypt לפני ה' אלוהינו שבעת
ימים ושבעת ימים ארבעה עשר יום lifnei Hashem Elokeinu shivat yamim veshivat
yamim arba'ah asar yom in front of ה' אלוהינו Hashem Elokeinu seven
and seven days fourteen days מכדי michdi כתיב ksiv so the verse
says וכל ישראל עמו קהל גדול vechol Yisrael imo kahal gadol all
of Israel one huge community okay and by the way the key
word here is קהל kahal because the verse by the special קרבן
korban? of בית דין Beis Din refers to it as הקהל ועשו
hakahal ve'asu okay so מלבוא חמת עד נחל מצרים למה לי milavo
Chamat ad Nachal Mitzrayim lama li why did it have to speak
about the borders שמע מינה הני הוא דאיקרי קהל shma mina hanei
hu de'ikri kahal only those that were from within those borders have
this concept of community of קהל kahal of true in tight sense
of this corporate identity I would say. We're not saying they're not
Jewish but we're saying this tight sense of corporate identity אבל הנך
לא איקרי קהל aval hanach lo ikri kahal those outside are not.
And you could understand that right I mean when you have sovereignty
now of course the because again this also assumes sovereignty it doesn't
assume just a majority living in the land under Roman rule right?
So when you are a people in your own land that creates
a very tight sense of קהל kahal a tight sense of corporate
identity which you don't have when you're living you know in a
foreign country. Okay. I mean you might have a sense of עם
am but not a sense of קהל kahal
okay.
Okay פשיטא pshita now the גמרא Gemara goes on to another point.
That was just a little drop that in in the middle of
everything else back to our discussion. Okay or back to another point
פשיטא מרובין ונתמעטו הני פלוגתא דרבי שמעון ורבנן pshita merubin venitma'atu hanei
plugta deRabbi Shimon verabanan let's say you have a case the following.
You have fifty-one percent of the community sins okay and following a
ruling of בית דין. Beis Din Before בית דין Beis Din becomes
aware of the error of their ruling okay some of those fifty-one
percent you had three million and one people sin and three million
don't. Before בית דין Beis Din becomes aware of their error five
people of the three million and one die. Okay so now when
בית דין Beis Din is aware of their error of the people
living only a minority of the people have actually sinned following בית
דין. Beis Din Would that be enough for בית דין Beis Din
to bring their קרבן? korban For בית דין Beis Din to bring
their קרבן korban they need a majority. Do you go by when
the act was done it was a majority? Or do you go
by when the obligation of the קרבן korban. kicks in when they
become aware that the sin was made and here it means that
בית דין Beis Din becomes aware?
So does בית דין Beis Din? have appeals? Do they have appeals?
בית דין Beis Din can't appeal their or this is the highest
court.
No but can't there's no
there's appeals for lower courts but that's a whole סנהדרין Sanhedrin discussion.
This is the high court themselves realizing retracting their own ruling realizing
they made a mistake.
So where were we? So okay ah so this is a debate
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים Chachamim and the debate
is whether a change of status happens. The following debate: a somebody
who there's a special קרבן korban. for somebody who sins as a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or as a king. Let's say this כהן
Kohen sinned as an individual. He ate חלב chelev he ate חמץ
chametz on פסח Pesach and then he became a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. And after becoming a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol he realized that
a week ago when he was not yet a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol he ate חמץ chametz on פסח. Pesach. Does he bring his
קרבן korban. as an individual who sinned? The sin was as a
layperson or a lay כהן. Kohen. The awareness when the חיוב chiyuv
of the קרבן korban kicked in was as a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. So they don't match okay? So in that case the חכמים
Chachamim say you still bring the קרבן korban. as an individual. You
go by the moment of sin. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
since the moment of awareness you were in a different status you
don't bring it. Okay. So the same would be here. When the
sin occurred the בית דין Beis Din was חייב chayav, in a
קרבן. korban. Now when the awareness came in there's not enough of
a רוב ציבור rov tzibur so the חכמים would say so according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you would not bring a קרבן korban.
in that
case.
Okay post-facto they die I don't see how it matters.
Because now is the moment that the חיוב chiyuv of the קרבן
korban. kicks in. It doesn't all go by the sin. The same
way רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it doesn't all go by the
sin when your status changes. You sinned as a layperson but you
became aware as a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay so I understand
your point though it's a little different because the status of בית
דין Beis Din. isn't different. It's measuring the conditions of the case.
I do understand the difference but the גמרא Gemara assumes it's the
same. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this הני פלוגתא דרבי
שמעון ורבנן hanei plugta deRabbi Shimon verabanan but how about the following
case מועטין ונתרבו מאי mu'atin venitrabu mai
if you had a minority who sinned and then they became a
majority and then בית דין Beis Din became aware. Now what's the
scenario? Other people? Yes but then it's obvious. So think about that
scenario. Okay. 3 million didn't sin and
2,999,995 did sin, and then six more sinned. Okay, that's the normal
case. People don't sin all at the same moment, they sin over
time. So Rashi is very smart. Rashi doesn't whatever, it doesn't let
me just say, Rashi says no, what happens is, no, it's not
that more people sinned. Then obviously, that more people are sinning based
on, בית דין Beis Din. becomes aware, בית דין Beis Din. brings
a קרבן. korban. No, no, no. Nobody more sinned. You have the
2,999,995 that sinned, and the 3 million that didn't. And of the
3 million that didn't, ten died. So if you were to do
the count now, because now a majority has sinned because some of
the majority of the other group died off. Okay, that's the case.
So מועטין ונתרבו מאי, Muatin veNisrabu Mai, what's the story? So in
that case, when the original sin occurred, you didn't have the right
numbers. Now at the moment of awareness, you have the right numbers.
מאי? Ma, מי פליגי רבי שמעון ורבנן? Mi pligi Rabbi Shimon veRabbanan?
Do they
would they still debate? Rabbi Shimon does בתר ידיעה, Basar Yediah, Rabbi
Shimon who goes by the moment of awareness, מחייב, Mechayav, he'd say
now you've got the right numbers. Now when you became aware, the
numbers are the majority, you bring a קרבן. ורבנן veRabbanan does בתר
חטאת, Basar Chatas, and the Rabbanan they go by the time of
sin, פטרי Patri would exempt you. או לא? O lo? מה? Ma?
Or not? מאי? mai? What would you say? ותסברא, veTisbras, and the
Gemara says, would you really think that's possible? That Rabbi Shimon would
say you go by the moment of being aware and it's and
you don't also need the moment of sin? אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי
שמעון דאזיל אף בתר ידיעה. Eima deShamas leih deRabbi Shimon deAzal Af
Basar Yediah. Rabbi Shimon requires two criteria: that the sin occurs at
a level of obligation and the awareness at the same level of
obligation. You sinned as a כהן, Kohen, you're aware as a כהן.
Kohen. The majority of the ציבור followed בית דין Beis Din. and
בית דין Beis Din. became aware when it was still a majority
of the ציבור. You need both criteria. היכא דהוי ידיעה וחטאת בחיוב,
Heichi davi Yediah veChatas beChiyuv, when you have both of them in
the same level of obligation. ידיעה דלא חטאת מי שמעת ליה? Yediah
delo Chatas mi Shamas leih? How could you think that when the
actual sin occurred בית דין Beis Din wasn't חייב chayav, and now,
because at the moment of awareness the numbers are different, now they're
going to be חייב? chayav Just the awareness without the sin? אם
כן ליתי
כהשתא, Im kein leisei kehashata, if that were to be true,
you should be bringing like now. אלא רבי שמעון חטאת וידיעה בעי.
Ela Rabbi Shimon Chatas veYediah Ba'i. He obviously needs both. Okay, so
and the Gemara does Can you
have a situation where someone commits an act but it just takes
effect later?
Well, that's true, but okay.
So that's a different case.
Okay. Okay.
Right. Oh, the
the line of אם כן ליתי כהשתא Im kein leisei kehashata means
in the case of let's say if Rabbi Shimon only went by
awareness, if the כהן Kohen sinned as a כהן Kohen and he
became aware as a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, why does Rabbi Shimon
say he doesn't bring a קרבן? If Rabbi Shimon really went by
moment of awareness, he should say bring a קרבן like a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Obviously he doesn't say that. Obviously it's not all
about the moment of awareness. It's about that the moment of awareness
has to be the same of the moment of sin. If it
was all about the moment of awareness, then bring a קרבן now
as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol even though you sinned as a
כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. So clearly for Rabbi Shimon it's about both
of them. Okay, אלא רבי שמעון חטא וידיעה בעי. Ela Rabbi Shimon
Chet veYediah Ba'i. He needs both of them to be the same.
So therefore in that case clearly nobody would bring a קרבן. Okay,
איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Now we have another question. הורו בית דין
חלב מותר ועשו מיעוט קהל וחזרו בית דין בהן וחזרו והורו ועשו
מיעוט אחר מאי.
Horu Beis Din
Cheilev Mutar veAsu miut kehal veChazru Beis Din bahen veChazru veHoru veAsu
miut acher mai. They gave a פסק. Psak. It's okay to eat
this forbidden fat.
40% of the people listened to them. Then they said, "Wait, wait,
wait, made a mistake." Okay, then they said, "Oh, you know what?
It really we were right the first time. It really is מותר
Mutar to eat this fat." And then another 20% listened to them.
Okay, so it's two separate rulings with them retracting in the middle.
Okay.
Okay, so מאי, what would you say? כיון דשתי ידיעות נינהו, Keivan
deShtei Yedios ninhu, since it was two different sets of being aware
that they had misruled and two different rulings, לא מצטרף, lo mitztarif,
they don't combine and it's cases of two separate instances and it's
not a case of רוב ציבור. Rov Tzibur. או דילמה כיון דהאי
והאי חלב הוא, O dilma keivan de'aidi ve'aidi cheilev hu, since it's
the same sin, מצטרף, mitztarif, it does combine. ואם תמצא לומר כיון
דהאי והאי חלב הוא מצטרף, VeIm timtza lomar keivan de'aidi ve'aidi cheilev
hu mitztarif, if you say because it's the same עבירה aveira that
they're ruling on it does combine, so מיעוט בחלב שעל גבי הקיבה
ומיעוט בחלב שעל גבי הדקין
מהו. miut becheilev she'al gabei hakeiva vemiut becheilev she'al gabei hadakin mahu.
Let's say it was about two different types of fat. First they
said the fat in this part
of the stomach
is okay, and 40% listened to them. And then they, "Wait, wait,
no, we made a mistake. It wasn't that fat that was okay,
it was this other fat that's okay." And then another 20% listened
to them. So so what do we say? הכא ודאי כיון דבתרי
קראי
קאתי לא מצטרף, Hacha vaday keivan debitrei krai ka'asi lo mitztarif, since
it's based on a different interpretation of two different verses, it doesn't
combine and they're separate rulings and you don't bring the special קרבן.
או דילמה כיון דהאי והאי חלב הוא, O dilma keivan de'aidi ve'aidi
cheilev hu, at the end of the day it's about the same
sin, מצטרף, mitztarif, it does combine.
ואם תמצא לומר שם חלב הוא VeIm timtza lomar shem cheilev hu
that... it does combine. מיעוט בחלב ומיעוט בדם, miyut be-cheilev u-miyut be-dam,
let's say it's ממש mamash two different sins. First they gave a
ruling about חלב cheilev and 30 percent listened to them and they
realized they made a mistake and then they gave a ruling about
דם dam and another 30 percent listened to them and they realized
they made a mistake there too. מהו? Mahu? הכא ודאי תרי איסורי
נינהו, Hacha vadai trei issurei ninhu, here it's clearly two separate violations,
וכיון דאין איסורן שוה לא מצטרף, ve-cheivan de-ein issuran shaveh lo mitztaref,
and since that they're not the same they don't combine, או דלמא,
odilma,
or do we say, כיון דקרבן שוה, keivan de-korban shaveh, they would,
since you would bring as an individual who accidentally ate חלב cheilev
and accidentally ate דם, dam, you'd bring the same קרבן, you'd bring
a חטאת, chatas, so maybe even separate עבירות aveiras combine for רוב
ציבור rov tzibbur following בית דין's Beis Din mistakes, not just one
mistake? מצטרף, mitztaref, maybe it would combine. ואם תמצא לומר, Ve-im timtza
lomar, if you say, כיון דקרבן שוה מצטרף, keivan de-korban shaveh mitztaref,
and it does combine because at the end of the day חלב
cheilev and דם dam is a similar קרבן, so we put it
all in one big
basket, אוקיי, okay, מיעוט בחלב ומיעוט בעבודת כוכבים מהו? miyut be-cheilev u-miyut
be-avodas kochavim mahu? How about now, because what I just want to
throw in here is what the גמרא's Gemara assuming when it says
חלב cheilev and דם dam combine is that really it means any
two עבירות aveiras combine, חלב cheilev and let's say a ruling about
an איסור עריות issur arayos would combine because it's all types of
cases, any type you would bring a קרבן, you know, anything would
combine. They could be experientially very different types of experiences, you know,
a חלב cheilev and doing עבודה avoda on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
right? All those things would combine and any two rulings of בית
דין Beis Din would combine. The only or three rulings or whatever,
the only case that would not combine would be a case
that the גמרא's Gemara asking would be a case of a ruling
of let's say חלב cheilev plus a ruling of עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. Why should עבודה זרה avoda zara not combine? Because when an
individual sins with עבודה זרה avoda zara he brings a different קרבן
than all other sins. So maybe that's the only one that doesn't
combine where we are right now. אוקיי, Okay, מיעוט בחלב ומיעוט בעבודת
כוכבים מהו, miyut be-cheilev u-miyut be-avodas kochavim mahu,
what would you say? הכא ודאי אין איסורן שוה ואין קרבנן שוה,
Hacha vadai ein issuran shaveh ve-ein korbanan shaveh, it's not the same
איסור issur and it's not even the same קרבן, או דלמא, odilma,
or do we say, כיון דאידי ואידי כרת הוא, keivan de-haidi ve-haidi
kares hu, at the end of the day both sins are sins
deserving כרת, kares, ומצטרף, u-mitztaref, it combines? תיקו, Teiku, so the גמרא
Gemara, doesn't know. So that's wild. You know, you would think that
when it's completely separate rulings it wouldn't combine, and presumably the גמרא
Gemara means even if בית דין Beis Din, becomes aware in the
middle, right? So and then I would like to ask, like, over
how much of a period of time? Ten years ago they gave
a ruling about חלב cheilev and they made a mistake and 20
percent of the people followed them. Then ten years later they made
a ruling about עבודה זרה avoda zara and that was a mistake
and another 20 percent. And then ten years after that they made
a ruling about יום כיפור Yom Kippur and another 20 percent follows.
So what, they all combine and now you bring a קרבן? Like
it's a little funny. You'd think you'd need there to be some
type of a more cohesion to this.
Anyway, is there any time lapse here? In other words, say, not
this question you brought up, but just say, take a single case.
They gave a ruling,
point right, and 20 percent...
Yeah, and eventually over the course of ten years, over the course
of ten years, 51 percent. Right, well אוקיי, okay, איבעיא להו ibaya
lehu is a separate question. Yeah, yeah, איבעיא להו ibaya lehu is
a separate question. But presumably there's no time frame, you know, if
over 20 years you got a majority that eventually followed them. There
is... Now the question is, let's say it's not the same בית
דין Beis Din, that's alive, it's not the same people. So we're
going to get to that too. How much do you think of
the בית דין Beis Din as an abstract entity, right? Do we
read like the Supreme Court, right? Is it... it's not about the
individuals who are on the court, right? So we'll take a look.
So then they're also going to come back to the question we
had about whether we
see
if you include the court as part of the...
Yeah, that was left as an open question, yeah, that's it's...
Whether it's an identity or...
Right, right, right. That's when they're sinning, are they looked at as
part of the court. But now I'm just talking about as the
בית דין beis din. who's חייב, chayav, do you look at, do
you focus on the individuals who make up the בית דין? beis
din Yeah.
Was there a concept of statute of limitations?
No,
not in הלכה. halacha. There's no statute of limitations. אוקיי, Okay, איבעיא
להו, ibaya lehu, they ask the question. הורו בית דין שחלב מותר
ועשו מיעוט הקהל, Horu Beis Din she-cheilev muttar ve-asu miyut ha-kahal, they
said it was מותר muttar and the minority of the congregation followed
them, ומת אותו בית דין, ve-meis oso Beis Din, so here's the
case exactly that I was talking about, and they died, ועמד בית
דין אחר, ve-amad Beis Din acher, and then another בית דין beis
din arose, וחזרו והורו ועשו מיעוט אחר, ve-chozru ve-horu ve-asu miyut acher,
and then they gave another ruling and another מיעוט did it. So
it's actually a court peopled by different people, you know, different judges.
Of course, the question is, let's say there's some judges that carried
over, you know. Anyway, what would you say? אליבא דמאן דאמר בית
דין מייתי, Aliba de-man de-amar Beis Din maity, if בית דין beis
din is the one that brings the קרבן in the special קרבן,
לא תיבעי לך, lo tiba-ei lach, דהא ליתנהו, de-ha leisnhu, certainly they
wouldn't bring in this case because it's not the same בית דין.
beis din Now again, I would sort of, to me that's not
obvious, you could think of them as an abstract entity. Now maybe
it's because it was the second ruling and the second ruling was
all by different people. But what about a case that it was
not a second ruling, it was one ruling and by the time
a majority sinned you had none of the original members of the
court sitting on the court, you got it? That case to me,
I would think it should be obvious that you think of them
as an abstract entity as a body, not as individuals. and the
court, which okay, was peopled by different people 20 years ago, but
it was the court's ruling, and the court has to bring a
קרבן. Okay, but here at least the גמרא, Gemara that's what I
would think. And then you have questions about what if you have
some individuals that carry over. But the גמרא Gemara says certainly if
it's a separate ruling, and it's all different individuals, you cannot combine
the two and say בית דין beis din has to bring a
קרבן because it's not the same בית דין. beis din, Okay.
How do you have a continuity of a legal system if you
are saying every time the court changes its population,
its rulings are
no longer applicable?
No, no, we're not saying the rules aren't applicable. We're saying that
the liability for that פסק psak of the earlier court that the
court holds in terms of their obligation to bring a קרבן, all
the rulings are binding. Okay, we're just saying that earlier court gave
a ruling, and that led a minority to sin, right? Now we're
a new court, okay, and we're giving, we're repeating the ruling, and
a minor, meaning it if the new court didn't say anything, then
people were still acting on the ruling of the old בית דין.
Beis Din Okay, but you're right, it is a little funny, like
why don't we just say that even if the new court repeated
the ruling, you didn't need them to repeat the ruling, the old
ruling was still in effect, so just say people are continuing to
sin, and yeah, you're right, it's a good question. Maybe, and you
know, anyway the גמרא Gemara certainly sounds like that there's this idea
that you need the same people or at least I don't know
some representation of the same people in order to bring a קרבן
for their mistake for their mistaken ruling if you assume the קרבן
is brought by the בית דין. Beis Din Okay. אלא כי תיבעי
לך, Ela ki teiba'i lach, yeah it is funny why it says
ועמד בית דין אחר וחזרו והורו. ve-amad Beis Din acher ve-chozru ve-horu.
It sounds like you need the new הוראה hora'ah separated the two
courts. You're right, like even if they weren't חזרו והורו, chozru ve-horu,
the old הוראה still in effect.
Anyway, it could be that, that could be the case, if the
old הוראה was still in effect, if there wasn't חזרו והורו, chozru
ve-horu, maybe like you said, it could be treated as one entity.
Right, I would think so, but then even with the חזרו והורו
chozru ve-horu even though that חזרו והורו chozru ve-horu was completely superfluous,
it somehow
stems the previous בית דין.
Beis Din, Maybe they say we're here, we want to reaffirm, you
know, there was controversial the previous ruling of the court, we're here
to reaffirm it, and that therefore, right, so maybe that is what
separates it off, so even if it was what do you call
it, even if it was superfluous. Okay, anyway, it says like this:
כי תיבעי לך אליבא דמאן דאמר ציבור מייתי. Ki teiba'i lach aliba
de-man de-amar tzibur mayti. If it's brought by the ציבור, מאי? ציבור
הכא, Tzibur hacha,
do we say okay, the community who sinned, they're still around, let
them bring the קרבן? או דילמא ידיעת בית דין דהורו בעינן? O
dilma yedias Beis Din de-horu ba'inan?
In order to be obligated, you need the בית דין that made
the initial ruling to be aware that they made a mistake, and
not some new בית דין to be aware they made a mistake,
that's not enough. And part of this could be that's very interesting,
because this gets to the question of how do you define an
objective mistake in terms of a court interpreting the תורה? Torah? Isn't
it whatever the court says is binding? So maybe part of what
you need to define it as an objective mistake is that the
court itself that gave the ruling recognizes the mistake, not that some
later court that says that the earlier ruling was a mistake. Okay,
now that's my read of it. The גמרא Gemara might be just
reading it in classic קרבן way. Classic קרבן lens is, as we
saw a minute ago, that the moment of awareness is part of
the חיוב chiyuv of the קרבן. So even if it's the ציבור
that is bringing it, maybe as a technical requirement, you need that
the ones who did the sin of ruling incorrectly, or the initial
act of ruling incorrectly, it's their awareness that is necessary, not their
retraction. I was trying to frame it as their retraction is necessary,
but this is saying no, just their awareness is necessary for the
obligation, even if it's the ציבור that brings the קרבן. תיקו, Teiku,
we don't know. Alright, let's just read a little bit further, if
you can give me, I mean if people have to leave it's
fine, but I just want to read to the משנה Mishnah so
we don't get extremely behind and it will go very fast. אמר
רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Yonatan, מאה שישבו להורות, meah she-yashvu le-horos, אין
חייבין עד שיורו כולן. ein chayavin ad she-yoru kulan. If a hundred
people sat to in the בית דין as opposed to 71, you
need all of them to פסקן pasken and presumably all of them
to, not just all of them to vote,
it has to be a unanimous vote, which is a completely new
idea, and the גמרא's gemara going to reject both of these assumptions.
Okay. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו, ve-im kol adas Yisrael
yishgu, if the entire community sinned, עד שישגו כולן, ad she-yishgu kulan,
they all have to be mistaken, it has to be unanimous the
vote in בית דין, which means nobody's ever going to bring this
קרבן. עד שתשווה הוראה בכל עדת ישראל, Ad she-tishveh hora'ah be-chol adas
Yisrael, until the entire בית דין, you know, is of one voice
in terms of the פסק. psak. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua, maybe that's like the גמרא gemara
that if all the בית דין opens up and says somebody is
חייב, you exempt them immediately. If there's no debate then actually it's
a proof that you're wrong. Okay, so maybe it's maybe that's part
of this idea too. That's not, anyway, but okay. Anyway, הכי נמי
מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense. דבכל התורה כולה קיימא לן
רובו ככולו. De-ve-chol ha-Torah kullah kaima lan rubo ke-kulo. Normally we say
a majority is like the whole thing. ואכתי כתיב כל העדה. Ve-achti
kesiv kol ha-edah. Why did it have to say the entire כל
העדה? kol ha-edah? שמע מינה, the entire means that it has to
be unanimous. Now once we're saying... it has to be unanimous, הוה
אמינא אפילו מאה hava amina afilu meah even if there are a
hundred because then it's not just about normal rules of בית דין.
Normal rules of בית דין majority would be enough. It's a special
הלכה, halacha, you need unanimous, and therefore, once that's true, if the
בית דין had more people in the court, you'd need all of
them as well. Now תנן, tenan, now we're going to reject this.
הורו בית דין וידע אחד מהן שטעו או תלמיד וראוי להוראה. horu
beis din veyada echad mehen shetou otam vedivrei lo ra. They gave
a ruling and one of them knew they made a mistake, ועשה
על פיהן בין שעשו ועשה עמהן בין שעשו ועשה אחריהן ובין שלא
עשו ועשה הרי זה חייב. veasah al pihen bein sheasu veasah imahen
bein sheasu veasah achareihen uvein shelo asu veasah harei ze chayav. So
that this guy who was on the court who knew they made
a mistake, he went ahead and he followed them, he's חייב because
he was, he knew they were wrong and he still did it.
מפני שלא תלה בבית דין. mipnei shelo talah beveis din. So the
גמרא gemara says one minute, here we have a member of the
court who disagrees with them.
האי הוא דחייב, hai hu dechayav, he's חייב, הא אחרי פטור, ha
acharei patur, somebody else is exempt. This constitutes a ruling even though
there's somebody who dissents. The whole case in the משנה mishna is
a dissenter and nevertheless, everybody else it would be considered like בית
דין gave the ruling. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי הלא לא
נגמרה הוראה, veamai halo lo nigmerah horaah, it's not that there was
unanimity. הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהרכין ההוא אחד מהן בראשו. hacha bemai
askinan kegon shehirchin hahu echad mehen berosho. When they were taking the
vote, the guy was nodding and in his, he wasn't verbally assenting
and in his head he was thinking these guys are all wrong,
they're, you know, institutional, right, exactly. In a formal sense, there was
a unanimity even though in this guy's mind, he was dissenting. But
if you were to ask us, we would say we had a
unanimous vote. תא שמע. ta shema. הורו בית דין וידע אחד מהן
שטעו ואמר להן. horu beis din veyada echad mehen shetou veamar lahen.
We have a ברייתא that says the guy said explicitly, טועין אתם,
toin atem, I'm telling you you're all making a mistake. הרי אלו
פטורים. harei elu pturim. Okay, so it says that is, that in
that case, okay, they are, okay, they are exempt because טעמא דאמר
להן טועין אתם דפטורים. tama deamar lahen toin atem depturim. Wait a
minute. They're exempt from bringing a קרבן because they were actually verbally,
that's actually interesting, I'm just drilling for some reason he gives his
verbal disagreement
and that's enough to say that they don't bring a קרבן. That's
pretty interesting. I guess because he didn't just say that he disagreed,
he said טועין אתם. toin atem. Anyway, טעמא דאמר להן טועין אתם
דפטורים. tama deamar lahen toin atem depturim. Okay, the reason is that
they're פטור, patur, so that is similar to this idea of unanimity,
but that's only if he verbally says טועין אתם. toin atem. הא
שתיק משתיק חייבין. ha shatik mashtik chayavin. If he was just silent,
okay, then and he wasn't sort of telling them they're making a
mistake, it sounds like if let's say he abstained, okay, וגמר להוראה,
vegomar lehoraah, then that would be a case of bringing a קרבן.
ואמאי הלא לא הורו כולן? veamai halo lo horu kulan? It wasn't
unanimous vote, like so here actually it does seem like a partial,
a partial whatever, you know, concession. It seems like if somebody verbally,
you know, disagrees and maybe I don't know if he has to
explain the, the harsh language of טועין אתם, toin atem, then actually
that's not the case of בית דין bringing a קרבן. But that's
not saying you need a unanimous vote. It sounds like if it
was an abstention, okay, then it would be a case of a
קרבן. ואמאי הלא לא הורו כולן? veamai halo lo horu kulan? They
didn't all rule it. אמרי הכא נמי כגון שהרכין בראשו. amri hacha
nami kegon shehirchin berosho. Alright, it would be a case that he
was like nodding, so it looked like it was unanimous even though
in his mind he was abstaining or whatever. But at least it's
a partial, you know, proof, not the idea that you need all
hundred to vote, but at least that, you know, if there's a
verbal opposition, okay, that that actually would not make this case of
בית דין bringing a קרבן. מתיב רב משארשיא. mesiv rav mesharshia. רב
משארשיא rav mesharshia challenges. סמכו רבותינו על דברי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
ועל דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק שהיו אומרים אין גוזרין גזירה על
הציבור אלא אם כן רוב ציבור יכולין לעמוד בה. samchu raboseinu al
divrei raban shimon ben gamliel veal divrei rabi elazar berabi tzadok shehayu
omrim ein gozrin gezeirah al hatzibur ela im kein rov tzibur yacholin
laamod bah. That we in other cases rely on their rulings that
they say you don't make a תקנה takana unless the majority of
the congregation can withstand, can can live up to it. ואמר רב
אדא בר אהבה מאי קרא, veamar rav ada bar ahavah mai kra,
what's the verse? במארה אתם נארים ואותי אתם קובעים הגוי כולו. bamairah
atem nairim veosi atem koveim hagoy kulo. You know, you are cursed
by this curse and you curse me, the entire congregation.
והכא דכתיב הגוי כולו, vehacha dechsiv hagoy kulo, your whole דיוק diyuk
before was from the language it said, it said כל עדת ישראל,
kol adat yisrael, that you needed it to be unanimous and you
needed everyone and so on. Here it says הגוי כולו hagoy kulo
ורובא ככולו דמי, veruva kechulo dami, but we interpret it to mean
the majority of the community has to be able to live up
to it. תיובתא דרבי יוחנן תיובתא. tiuvta derabi yochanan tiuvta. So that
was the, the least directly relevant of all the proofs, but it's
the one the גמרא Gemara takes as conclusive. So you're right. You
do not need a unanimity to, you don't need all hundred if
a hundred sit in, you still go by normal rules of בית
דין, you need the core seventy-one, and you don't need a unanimous
yes vote, but it does seem like a verbal opposition would make
a difference. But, but people could dissent or people could certainly abstain
and you don't need a unanimous yes vote. Okay? Did you have
this?
Don't you just have this מלאכי Malachi in the הפטרה? Haftorah?
Oh, that's true. Yeah. So okay so גמרא says like this: ואלא
מאי כל אתא כמה רחמנא? Ve'ella mai kol ata kamma rachmana? So
what does the word כל kol there for mean? הכי קאמר. Hachi
ka'amar. איכא כולם הויא הוראה ואי לא לא הויא הוראה. Ikka kullam
havya horaa ve'lo lo havya horaa. You need all of them to
be in the court. Okay? You don't need all of them to
vote yes, you need a full attendance of the court, but you
don't need them all to vote yes. אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua, now because we're talking about this idea of all of them
present and a whole court and so on, he ends with the
following point: י' שיושבין בדין, Yod she'yoshvin badin, if ten people are
sitting in judgment, even though some of them are superfluous, you don't
have a בית דין of ten because we already were discussing like
a בית דין of a hundred, so what's the benefit of having
extra bodies if you don't need them? So he
says הקולר תלוי בצואר כולם, Ha'kolar talui b'tzavar kullam, the yoke of
judgment is around all of their necks. They all share in the
responsibility. פשיטא, Peshita, isn't that obvious? No, הא קמשמע לן דאפילו תלמיד
בפני רבו, Ha kamashma lan da'afilu talmid bifnei rabbo, that even if
one of them is just more or less an extra body, right,
he's a student in the presence of his רבי, so you could
say he's not taking his own responsibility, he's just following whatever his
רבי says. No, if you're sitting on the court, even if you're,
you know, not as big of an authority, you share in the
responsibility of the judgment of the court. Okay? Doesn't, you know, it's
not necessarily the thing that's going to attract people to being judges.
But now the גמרא says the following: רב הונא כי הוי נפיק
לבי דינא, Rav Huna ki havei nafik l'vei dina, when he would
go out to בית דין, מייתי עשרה תנאי דבי רב לקמיה, Meisi
asara tarna'ei d'vei Rav l'kamei, he would bring ten of the תנאי,
tarna'im, which were again, not like the תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim, the
memorizers from רב house, he would sort of, you know, he'd חאפ
chap some young ישיבה בחורים Yeshiva bochurim to come sit in his
court, כי היכי דלימטי שיבא מכשורא, Ki heichi d'nimti shiva meikashura, and
obviously they wouldn't, you know, have a different vote than him, they
would just follow his lead, but because there were ten of them,
each one would get a little splinter from the beam. It's a
phrase, which means that everybody would share
in the responsibility so it does,
it takes all of the weight off of one person. Okay? And
therefore now, you know, if we were doing a wrong thing, at
least each one of us is not fully responsible, we can distribute
some of
the
responsibility.
רב אשי כי הוי מייתי טרפה לקמיה, Rav Ashi ki havei meisi
treifa l'kamei, when he would have a טרפה treifa he would have
to decide on, מייתי עשרה טבחי ממתא מחסיא, Meisi asara tivchei m'masa
machasya, he'd get ten of the שוחטים shochtim together, and you could
say he wants their practical experience. Okay? But it could also just
be: No, he says: Hey guys, come let me teach you something.
You know, like I remember when I was in ישיבה, Yeshiva, you
know, my רבי took me once to like see how a חליצה
chalitza was done, how a גט get was, and: Hey, call the
שוחטים, shochtim, come let me involve you in this. So even if
they weren't adding their own opinions, maybe they were bringing their experience,
but even if they weren't, he says this will distribute the sense
of responsibility. ומוסיף קמייהו אמר כי היכי דלימטי שיבא מכשורא, Umoseif kameiham
amar ki heichi d'nimti shiva meikashura, they should get a splinter from
the beam. Okay?
Like we have labor courts and some...